<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Designs of France against England and Holland discovered, or, The intrigues of that crown for the utter ruine of both those nations, laid open.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1686</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 42 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A35780</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1177</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R197</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12264609</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12264609</idno>
            <idno type="VID">57967</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A35780)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 57967)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 180:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Designs of France against England and Holland discovered, or, The intrigues of that crown for the utter ruine of both those nations, laid open.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1686]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Opposing James II's foreign policy.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Date of publication taken from Wing.</note>
                  <note>"With allowance."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>James --  II, --  King of England, 1633-1701.</term>
               <term>Louis --  XIV, --  King of France, 1638-1715.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  James II, 1685-1688.</term>
               <term>France --  History --  Louis XIV, 1643-1715.</term>
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  1648-1714.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="plans">
            <pb facs="tcp:57967:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:57967:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE DESIGNS OF FRANCE AGAINST England and Holland Diſcovered: Or, the Intrigues of that Crown, for the utter Ruine of both thoſe Nations, laid open.</head>
            <div type="license_to_print">
               <p>
                  <hi>WITH ALLOWANCE.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="notice">
               <head>ADVERTISEMENT <hi>to the</hi> READER.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THESE Papers</hi> (which were intended to be publiſh'd before this time, had the <hi>Preſs</hi> been open for ſuch Truths) plainly diſcover the cunning <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigues,</hi> Wicked <hi>Deſigns,</hi> and Unchriſtian <hi>Practices</hi> of the <hi>French</hi> King, for the Overthrow of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> and with them the <hi>Proteſtant Religion.</hi> If this Account be (as 'tis hoped) approved of, a further Information may be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected from the ſame Hand.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="French against English" type="plans">
               <p>A <hi>Diſcovery</hi> of the <hi>Deſigns</hi> of <hi>France</hi> againſt <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>HENRY</hi> VIII. King of <hi>England,</hi> did, in his time, cauſe a Medal to be ſtampt with a Hand ſtretch'd out of a Cloud, holding a Balance in equal poiſe, whereof both the Scales repreſented <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> with this Motto, <hi>Cui adhaereo praeeſt,</hi> My Alliance weighs it down. It ſeems that Prince well knew his own Might; whereas now <hi>England</hi> may be compared to an Ox, who being inſenſible of his own ſtrength, quietly ſubmits himſelf to the Yoke. Evident it is, That <hi>England</hi> has many Advantages beyond other Kingdoms, but eſpecially
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:57967:2"/>this, that being an Iſland, it can eaſily ſecure it ſelf againſt any Foreign Force; they that intend an Invaſion againſt it, muſt be obliged to croſs the Seas, and ſtruggle with the Winds and Waves, and all the hazards and dangers of that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable Element, beſides a very potent Fleet, which alone is ſufficient to deter their hardieſt Enemy, from any ſuch Deſign. Now this being ſo, 'tis manifeſt that the King of <hi>England</hi> (having Peace and a ſtrict Alliance with <hi>Holland</hi>) can over-balance the Party he deſigns againſt.</p>
               <p>This is a Truth, <hi>France</hi> is ſo fully convinc'd of, that notwithſtanding the great Antipathy there is between both Nations, he has hitherto ſpar'd nothing, and is ſtill turning every ſtone, to take off <hi>England</hi> from its true Intereſt, and to engage it on his ſide, or at leaſt oblige it to ſtand Neuter, and to be an idle, uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd Spectator of the horrid Tragedy the <hi>French</hi> King acts upon the Theatre of <hi>Europe,</hi> becauſe he well knows that <hi>England</hi> is better able to prevent it, and ſpoil his Sport, than any other State or Kingdom whatſoever, and reſcue <hi>Europe</hi> from the Univerſal Slavery he prepares for it.</p>
               <p>Would the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>England</hi> only be pleaſed to open his Eyes, faſt cloſed with the enchanted ſlumbers of the <hi>French Dalilah,</hi> to take a view of his own Strength and true Intereſt, he ſhould ſoon find himſelf making another Figure amongſt the Princes of <hi>Europe,</hi> than of late Years he hath done, and with eaſe mount that high degree of Power and Glory, of being the profeſt Umpire of the Univerſe, the Sovereign Mediator and Decider of Controverſies, and the Giver of Peace to all <hi>Europe,</hi> which <hi>France,</hi> in a vain Bravado, pretends to, when indeed he is the ſole Troubler of it.</p>
               <p>To arrive at this tranſcendent pitch of Grandeur and Authority, two things only (which the King of <hi>England</hi> may do when he pleaſes) are requiſite. The firſt is, That his Majeſty do comport himſelf ſo, as to engage the Love of his People, and keep a right Underſtanding between him and his Parliament. And the ſecond, That he enter into a ſtrict Alliance with <hi>Holland,</hi> living in ſincere Amity, perfect Union, and good Correſpondence with them, in order to their common Defence and Security<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The former of theſe is very eaſie, and the King will do it, as ſoon as he ſhall reſolve to deſire nothing of his Parliament, but what is agreeable with the Laws of the Realm, which by his Coronation Oath he is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to obſerve and maintain; and the latter will be found to be of abſolute ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, as ſoon as the King of <hi>England</hi> ſhall pleaſe to ſtop his Ears to the falſe Suggeſtions of <hi>France,</hi> and ſtifle thoſe Jealouſies and Reſentments which his Emiſſaries daily buzze into his Head; there being nothing to fear for <hi>England</hi> from the <hi>States,</hi> whoſe deſire is not to enlarge their Dominions (as <hi>France</hi> do's) by invading thoſe of their Neighbors, but only to keep what God has given them, and to maintain their Subjects in the Liberty they now enjoy.</p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:57967:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>This <hi>France</hi> ſo well knows, that he leaves no Stone unturn'd to prevent it, and continually ſends forth ſome crafty turbulent Spirits, to ſowe the Seeds of Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and Miſunderſtanding between the <hi>King</hi> and his <hi>Parliament.</hi> Thus the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of <hi>France</hi> was at work, to exaſperate the <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> Party againſt the <hi>Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians,</hi> and again the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> and other <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> againſt them, making them believe that the <hi>Biſhops</hi> favoured <hi>Popery,</hi> and would not fail to prove Turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coats, as ſoon as a favourable Opportunity ſhould be offer'd them, and that the King did incline the ſame way, with a thouſand like Suggeſtions, which ſo ſet the People againſt the <hi>King,</hi> and filled the <hi>Parliament</hi> with ſuch Jealouſies, that they often granted his then Majeſty but very little of what he demanded, and gave him ſo much work at Home, that he had no leiſure to conſider what was done Abroad. It was <hi>France</hi> that firſt kindled the Civil Wars in the time of <hi>Charles</hi> I. which coſt <hi>England</hi> ſo much Blood, the <hi>French</hi> Ambaſſador that was then at that Court, boaſting at his Return from thence, <hi>That he had kindled a Fire in</hi> England, <hi>which ſhould not be quenched of a long time, and that the</hi> Engliſh <hi>for</hi> 20 <hi>Years to come, would not be in a condition to claim any thing of</hi> France.</p>
               <p>To the kindling of this Unhappy Flame, one Father <hi>Joſeph,</hi> a <hi>Capuchine</hi> Fryar, did much contribute under-hand, by means of the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> eſpecially thoſe that were in the Parliament's Army. But now ſince the King of <hi>England</hi> has thought good to change his Religion, <hi>France</hi> alſo has alter'd his Battery, and turn'd all his great Guns againſt the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and ſo far are the minds of Men irrita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt one another, that his <hi>Britiſh</hi> Majeſty will not, this good while, be in a condition to look any where elſe but at Home, where he is like to meet with ſo many Croſſings and Thwartings of the Deſigns he is carrying on, that he will find it a hard matter to break through them, and accompliſh the thing he aims at, and ſo zealouſly affects. And whil'ſt theſe Heart-burnings continue between the <hi>King</hi> and his <hi>People,</hi> he will be forced continually to be upon his Guard, and to keep his Forces about him, and caſt about his Thoughts how to raiſe a Fund to maintain them, and thereby give an opportunity to <hi>France</hi> to poſſeſs himſelf of the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> and of <hi>Spain</hi> too, in caſe that King ſhould chance to dye, which happy hour, <hi>France,</hi> with a great deal of Impatience, looks for.</p>
               <p>As for the ſecond point, <hi>viz.</hi> a League with the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Privinces,</hi> and a right underſtanding and good Correſpondence between thoſe two Governments, to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe all Powers that would invade and trouble the Peace of Chriſtendom, it is certain that the States for their parts would moſt gladly embrace the Propoſal, if they ſaw any likelihood of engaging therein with ſafety, and being ſeconded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on occaſion; of which indeed there is but little probability as long as affairs ſhall continue, in the condition wherein they are at preſent. This indeed is the thing, which of all others <hi>France,</hi> would be very loth to ſee, becauſe the hearty Union
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:57967:3"/>of theſe two Governments, would in all probability put a ſtop to the <hi>French</hi> Kings undertakings, overturn all his deſigns, and put him into an utter incapacity of attempting any thing againſt the Peace of <hi>Nimeguen,</hi> or the Truce with the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror. But <hi>France</hi> carries a watchful eye to prevent this Capital inconvenience, and that by an aſſiduous fomenting and cheriſhing feuds and animoſities between thoſe two Nations, and improving every occurrence to this purpoſe: of which we have a freſh inſtance in the buſineſs of <hi>Bantam,</hi> which had been long ago made up, but that <hi>France</hi> (who finds it beſt fiſhing in troubled waters) thinks it more for his Intereſt, that it ſhould remain undertermin'd; which is the very reaſon why it was never made an end of, but kept as a reſerve for a quarrel upon occaſion. That there can be nothing ſo evidently deſtructive of the <hi>French</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns as this Union between <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Holland</hi> is very apparent; <hi>England</hi> can when it pleaſes overturn the projects of <hi>France</hi> againſt the <hi>Spaniſh Netherlands;</hi> neither could that King ever have taken <hi>Luxemburg,</hi> if the late <hi>King of England</hi> had had the leaſt inclination to oppoſe him in that attempt, but the <hi>French</hi> King ſo well knew to take him by the blind ſide, that he did not perceive the miſchief, till the City was taken. It was a Capital Error for <hi>England</hi> to part with <hi>Dunkirk;</hi> a place that open'd a paſſage for them to <hi>France</hi> and <hi>the Low Countries;</hi> but it would make the matter much worſe, if all thoſe Countries ſhould be fain to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to the Tyranny of <hi>Lewis the Great,</hi> and he by this means ſhould join <hi>Newport</hi> and <hi>Oſtend</hi> to <hi>Dunkirk;</hi> for then would <hi>Fluſhing</hi> follow by Conſequence, and that King be put into a condition to diſpute the Soveraignty of the Sea with his <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh Majeſty,</hi> and deſtroy the Navigation and Commerce of this flouriſhing King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. Having got thus far, he would proceed to an entire conqueſt of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces,</hi> which point being once gain'd by him, <hi>England</hi> would have but little reaſon to flatter it ſelf with the hopes of a better Lot. Renowned Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> of happy Memory, was ſo ſenſible of what is here alledged, that ſhe told <hi>Monſieur de Sully,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> Kings Ambaſſadour at her Majeſties Court, that neither <hi>France</hi> nor <hi>England,</hi> nor any other Prince or State whatſoever, ought to lay any claim to the <hi>Low Countries,</hi> and that ſhe would never ſuffer the King his Maſter to make the leaſt attempt that way. Upon which <hi>Monſieur de Sully</hi> ſent word to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, <hi>that notwithſtanding the oppoſite ſentiments of the Queen, his Majeſty might by means of great forces, keep his friends within their own bounds, and poſſeſs himſelf of ſuch Territories and Cities in the</hi> Low Countries, <hi>as ſhould be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to joyn</hi> France <hi>and the</hi> United Provinces <hi>wholly and inſeparably together: which was</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>the only way to reſtore</hi> France <hi>to its Primitive Grandure and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and pitch it above the reſt of Chriſtendome; for if by any means the Provinces of</hi> Luxemburg, Juliers, Mark, Mons, Aix, <hi>and</hi> Cleves, <hi>were once <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited to</hi> France, <hi>there was no doubt, but the reſt of the Country would be forc'd to follow their example, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:57967:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>deprived of all communication and correſpondence with the reſt of the world.</hi> Sure it is <hi>France</hi> has always inclin'd this way, ſince they have obſerved that they could not compaſs their deſign by <hi>Italy,</hi> as the <hi>Romans</hi> of old; which Conqueſt tho it be the intereſt of all Princes of <hi>Europe</hi> to prevent, as much as in them lies; yet it is evident that theſe two States who are nearer at hand, and can better do it, are the moſt of all concern'd to put a ſtop to the Progreſs of the <hi>French</hi> in the <hi>Low Countries,</hi> which would not fail to be attended with diſmal conſequences to them, as before mention'd. As for <hi>Spain,</hi> it is a Body deprived of the uſe of its Limbs, and to which nothing remains but that of its Tongue, <hi>viz.</hi> To pray and entreat its good Friends and Allies not to forſake it. But none can do more than <hi>England,</hi> towards the Preſervation of the <hi>Low Countries;</hi> and if his <hi>Britiſh Majeſty</hi> had not promiſed to ſtand ſtill, <hi>Luxemburg</hi> would ſtill be in the State wherein it was formerly, and a Bone for <hi>France</hi> to pick. The <hi>French</hi> King is ſo well aware of this, that he takes all the care he can to keep the <hi>King of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> on his ſide, or at leaſt to remain Neuter, in caſe he will not declare himſelf for him. To which purpoſe he ſpares nothing, neither Preſents, Penſions, nor Arts, to keep all ſafe on that ſide. But alas, this Money and thoſe Preſents of <hi>France</hi> are like a Snake hid under Roſe-leaves. This is a Smiling Lip, which hereafter will prove a deadly Sting. They are Iron Chains gilded o're to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Eyes of thoſe who now admires what hereafter they will have occaſion to lament, if they do not betimes diſcover the Cheat of him who deſigns to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlave them. <hi>England</hi> ſubſiſts by ballancing the Crown of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> and keeping them in equal poiſe; wherefore it muſt needs be the Intereſt of that Kingdom by all means poſſible to prevent the <hi>Low Countries</hi> from becoming an occaſion to the overweight of <hi>France,</hi> leſt by this means it ſhould be incapacita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to maintain the Balance of <hi>Europe</hi> for time to come. For if ever by ill For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune the <hi>French King</hi> ſhould make himſelf Maſter of all the 17 Provinces as 'tis his great Aim, and may eaſily be brought to paſs if the States be not ſeconded, what condition will <hi>England</hi> then be in? <hi>France</hi> will be ſtronger than they at Sea and in the <hi>Indies,</hi> and conſequently interrupt their Commerce and Navigation, by keeping a great Fleet abroad, eſpecially in the Channel, ſo that nothing ſhall be able to ſtir out of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Havens, but by their leave, and upon the leaſt oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion the total Conqueſt of <hi>England</hi> muſt needs enſue, and that without Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, there being no body in a condition to ſtave off their final Ruin.</p>
               <p>Moreover the true Intereſt of <hi>England</hi> is to keep <hi>France</hi> low, as well to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Dominion of the Sea, as to find a favourable occaſion to recover thoſe ancient Dominions the <hi>French King</hi> keeps from them, as are the Dukedoms of <hi>Britany</hi> and <hi>Normandy, Poictou, Languedoc,</hi> nay <hi>France</hi> it ſelf; for of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of the King of <hi>England</hi> with <hi>Margaret</hi> Daughter to <hi>Philip the Fair,</hi> was
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:57967:4"/>born <hi>Henry</hi> the Fifth King of <hi>England,</hi> who had the ſame Right to <hi>France</hi> as the <hi>Dauphin</hi> has to <hi>Spain.</hi> The Three Sons of King <hi>Philip the Fair,</hi> viz. <hi>Lewis Hutin, Philip the Tall,</hi> and <hi>Charles the Fair,</hi> died all without Iſſue Male: And it was not till after this, when the King of <hi>England</hi> proſecuted his Right to the Kingdom of <hi>France,</hi> that the <hi>Salick Law</hi> was made, upon a Speech of the Biſhop of <hi>Beauvais</hi>'s in the Aſſembly of the States, in which he endeavoured to make out from an alluſion to that place of the Goſpel, <hi>The Lillies Spin not;</hi> that the Crown of <hi>France</hi> ought not to fall to the Diſtaff. But that Law could not preſcribe to time paſt, but only to that which was to come, and conſequently could not inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidate the King of <hi>England</hi>'s Pretenſions. After this, <hi>Henry</hi> the Fifth entring <hi>France</hi> with a powerful Army, and having defeated the <hi>French</hi> in ſeveral Battels, Married <hi>Catharin</hi> Daughter to <hi>Charles</hi> the Sixth; and in the Year 1441, it was concluded that <hi>Henry</hi> ſhould be King of <hi>France. Iſabella</hi> alſo who was Queen of <hi>France,</hi> and Mother to <hi>Catharin</hi> Queen of <hi>England,</hi> made her laſt Will in Favour of her Son in Law, declaring him therein the ſole Heir of all her Eſtate and of the Crown, which encreaſes the juſt Pretenſions, and ſtrengthens the Rights of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to the <hi>Kingdom of France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Had the <hi>French</hi> King but half the Pretenſions to <hi>England,</hi> which the King of <hi>England</hi> has to <hi>France,</hi> the World would ſoon hear of nothing but <hi>Manifeſto's</hi> to prove them juſt, as he calls all he does.</p>
               <p>So that the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>England</hi> ought upon all occaſions and in all reſpects to ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect <hi>France,</hi> and to beware of him as a moſt dangerous Enemy, who flatter'd and humour'd his late Majeſty, only to lull him aſleep, that he might play his game without being diſturb'd or interrupted by him, who, whenever it ſhall pleaſe him to mind and be true to his own Intereſt, will undoubtedly carry the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſtroke in the Affairs of <hi>Europe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis therefore no wonder that King <hi>Lewis</hi> the Fourteenth, ſpared nothing that might ſupply the Neceſſities or provide for the Pleaſures of the late King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, as <hi>Monſieur Barillon,</hi> and the Dutcheſs of <hi>Portſmouth</hi> can Witneſs. But I muſt tell you, that the <hi>French</hi> King confiders no Body, whether Prince or private Perſon, any further than as they may be ſervicable to promote his own ends; Yea Vertue it ſelf is not eſteemed by him, except it go hand in hand with his Intereſt. Do but confider what account he made of the <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>Princeſſes</hi> of <hi>England</hi> in <hi>Cromwels</hi> time; were they not obliged to leave <hi>France,</hi> and to ſeek for Entertainment elſewhere? And it is notorious that he never contributed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing towards the late Kings Reſtauration, till it was paſt his skill to hinder it.</p>
               <p>So that upon the whole, neither the Reſentment of the Royal Family, nor the Intereſt of <hi>England,</hi> will allow of ſuch ſtrict Alliances with <hi>France,</hi> as might tie up the King of <hi>Englands</hi> hands, and make him an idle Spectator, whilſt <hi>Lewis the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:57967:4"/>Great</hi> makes himſelf Maſter of the <hi>Low Countries;</hi> but on the contrary he muſt always be ready to oppoſe any the leaſt Attempt he ſhall make toward it, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king uſe in the mean time of the Six Regiments he has in <hi>Holland</hi> (which the States will not deny him on that account) till he can ſend ſome other Troops o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to <hi>Flanders.</hi> I am perſwaded that thoſe Six Regiments will be able to make Head againſt double the number of <hi>Frenchmen;</hi> and when <hi>England</hi> ſhall thus be pleaſed but to ſhew its Teeth, all <hi>Europe</hi> will thereby be ſafe, <hi>Reſiſt the Devil, and he will fly from you; but if you fear him, he will make you his Slaves. France</hi> has cut out work enough for King <hi>James</hi> the Second, and the buſineſs that he hath taken in hand is ſo great, that many people fear, and others hope, he'l never com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs it. 'Tis not a time to alter old Laws, when the Enemy is at the Gates; 'tis not always ſeaſonable for a King to act the <hi>Miſſionary,</hi> but much more requiſite that he ſhew himſelf a brave Soldier and good Politician. All the World was in expectation of great things from his Majeſty; his Courage put all <hi>Europe</hi> in hopes of an univerſal Relief, and ſome Reſpite for <hi>Spain,</hi> but how has he fruſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and befool'd their Hopes, whilſt his ſole Study is to pleaſe the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> and to kindle a Fire in his own Kingdom, which probably he will never be able to quench when he would, as long as he dares not Convene a Free Parliament.</p>
               <p>As <hi>Spain</hi> became depopulated by the departure of the <hi>Moors,</hi> ſo is <hi>France</hi> greatly weaken'd and impoveriſhed by the <hi>Dragoon Converſions,</hi> and flight of the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants;</hi> and the <hi>French</hi> King would fain ſee <hi>England</hi> brought to the ſame paſs. 'Tis a high Preſumption to rob God of his Right, 'tis to him the Honour of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting does belong, that work ſurpaſſing the Power and Activity of a Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. So leaving that care to God, the King of <hi>England</hi> ought to lay out his En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours about preſerving his Dominions from becoming a Prey to that Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Prince, by obliging him to keep within his own bounds, and not to encroach upon his Neighbours Territories; and in ſo doing, the King will make good the Hopes and Expectation <hi>Europe</hi> had conceived of him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="French against Dutch Republic" type="plans">
               <head>
                  <hi>The</hi> Deſigns <hi>of</hi> France <hi>againſt the</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces.</head>
               <p>AFter the <hi>States</hi> of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces</hi> had by their Powerful Arms con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained <hi>Spain</hi> to acknowledge them a Free State, who owed Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to none but God alone; they were for a time the Object of their Neighbours Admiration and Envy, every one endeavouring to Court and make Alliances with this growing State, which began to be lookt upon as the Umpire of <hi>Europe:</hi> But this high Reputation of theirs has ſuffer'd a notable Eclipſe ſince the War of 1672, when <hi>France</hi> having brought them to the very brink of Deſtruction, pleas'd himſelf with the thoughts of ſeeing them tumble
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:57967:5"/>headlong into the Pit he had digged for them; neither would he have been miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in his hopes, had not the people given a ſudden and unlookt for turn to the face of Affairs, by declaring the <hi>Prince of Orange Stadthouder;</hi> the Providence of Almighty God at the ſame time concurring with their Endeavours to preſerve that ſmall Spot of Ground, by confounding and daunting their Enemies, who af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the taking of <hi>Naerden,</hi> were ſtruck with ſuch a Panick Fear, that the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ran a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, none purſuing them. Now what contributed moſt to the Miſchiefs they were involved in at that time, was, that beſides the Treaſonable Correſpondences which <hi>France</hi> held with ſome principal Members of that Government, they had neither any good Troops, nor a Commander in Chief; and relying on the Peace and fair Promiſes of <hi>France,</hi> they were well nigh lull'd aſleep by that fatal Melo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, whilſt that King was hard at work to undermine the Foundation of their dear bought Liberties and Government. We find in time of Peace the Soldiers grow Idle, as well as their Arms ruſty. Eaſe pleaſeth and flatters us, and Men are ſoon perſwaded to lay aſide the Exerciſe of Arms, to betake themſelves to a more gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful way of Living; ſo that when the Enemy approached, they are readier to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace ſhame when joyned with Profit and Pleaſure, than to ſtrive for Glory ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounded with difficulties and dangers— <hi>France</hi> knew very well, that ſo long as the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces</hi> had no <hi>General,</hi> that Soldiery could not be but in a very bad Condition, and incapable of defending them from the Attempts of a powerful Enemy; wherefore he took ſpecial Care, by cunning Practices and falſe Sug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions (exaſperating the Minds of the oppoſite Party) to prevent the <hi>Prince of Orange's</hi> being advanced to thoſe places of Truſt and Dignity <hi>His Royal Highneſs</hi> is now ſo deſervedly poſſeſſed of. By this means the <hi>States</hi> grew daily weaker and weaker, their Troops were diſſipated, their Fortifications neglected, their Strongeſt Holds went to decay, their Magazins were unfurniſh'd, whilſt <hi>France</hi> was raiſing Troops under-hand, and making Secret Alliances with <hi>England,</hi> the Elector of <hi>Cologne,</hi> and <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſhop of Munſter,</hi> in order to their final Ruin. <hi>Du Pleſſis</hi> is much in the right, when he ſaith, <hi>That a State is not to be judged ſtrong or weak, but with relation to the ſtrength or weakneſs of its Neighbours, and that it is upon that ſcore that Wiſe Princes endeavour to keep themſelves (as much as they can) in equal potſe with their Neighbours, to the end, they continue in Peace and Amity toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; for as ſoon as this fails, all Peace and Good Correſpondence are diſſolved, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing only grounded upon a mutual fear or eſteem for one another.</hi> Which is ſo true, that a Prudent Prince is always jealous of the leaſt advance or motion of his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, tho in a time of Truce or Peace, and is continually upon his Watch, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to be informed of his Deſigns before they be brought forth; for by this means, he puts him by his Meaſures, and fruſtrates his Purpoſes. In which point many Princes and States, who are too ſaving, fail very oft, and this Covetouſneſs
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:57967:5"/>of theirs, coſts them and their People very dear, by occaſioning a moſt Expenſive War, vvhich at the firſt by Precaution might have been prevented with a ſmall Matter. <hi>France</hi> is ſo well Informed of this Truth, that they neglect nothing in ſuch Caſes, and their <hi>Ambaſſadors</hi> in all the <hi>Courts of Europe</hi> are ſupplied with Moneys for that very purpoſe, who knowing they cannot pleaſe their Maſter better, than by Corrupting one or more of the Miniſters of the Prince or State at whoſe Court they reſide, are Day and Night contriving for it, and ſpare no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to bring it about. Yea, when it happens that they cannot prevail with the Man himſelf they aim at, they endeavour to gain his Wife, or in caſe they chance to be ſo unhappy as to fail there alſo, they condeſcend to make their Application to ſome of their Children; nay, ſo humble are they, and ſuch Slaves to their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter's Ambition, that they will not ſtick to bribe their Servants, and furniſh them with Moneys proportionable to the Service they are able and willing to do them. Theſe are the Maxims that ſpeed their Deſigns wonderful well in ſuch States as are governed by many Heads, as the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces,</hi> which are a great Bar to the <hi>French King</hi> in his aim of Conquering the <hi>Spaniſh Netherlands,</hi> who very well knows, that being Maſter of the one, he cannot miſs of the other, His great buſineſs therefore is, to lull the <hi>States</hi> of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces</hi> aſleep with a Truce, which he will break when he pleaſes, being in hopes that their Forces will in the mean time be neglected, in laying out themſelves wholly to propagate and encourage Trade and Navigation. For that King is well aware, that the <hi>States</hi> being awake and ſtanding on their Guard, will never conſent to his poſſeſſing himſelf of the <hi>Spaniſh Netherlands,</hi> at leaſt they ought not to do it, ſince that it is the only Bar and Rampart which hinders <hi>France</hi> from overwhelming them, which they ought therefore by all means to endeavour to preſerve whole and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, as one would his Neighbours Houſe from being ſet on Fire. What pains did not <hi>Count d' Avaux</hi> take to ſet one Province againſt the other, and to ſow Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions among the Cities of <hi>Holland,</hi> how buſie was he at <hi>Amſterdam?</hi> What Proffers or Promiſes did he ſpare to bring it about? Which is a thing ſo publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly known from that Ambaſſador's frequent Journeys to that great City, that the very Children were not ignorant of it. We muſt not imagine that <hi>Mombas</hi> was alone engag'd in his Treaſon againſt that State, but rather that he eſcaping into <hi>France,</hi> has left ſeveral behind him, that walk in the dark, and are not yet diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered. The beſt on't is, that <hi>Count d' Avaux</hi> begins now to be known, and his Inſinuations not believed, he having but too long impoſed upon the Credulity and good Nature of many, who now perceiving the Cheat, will ſcarcely ſuffer themſelves to be decoy'd a ſecond time. And as <hi>France</hi> was diligent to ſow theſe Diviſions and Jealouſies amongſt them at home, ſo was he no leſs Induſtrious in fomenting Differences between <hi>England</hi> and them, as knowing very well that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:57967:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>theſe Neighbouring Powers when joyn'd together, are able to give check to his Pride, and ſet bounds to his Ambition. How pleaſing a ſight is it to the <hi>French King</hi> to ſee them engag'd againſt each other, and purſuing his Intereſts at ſo vaſt an Expence of their own Blood and Treaſure? The laſt War betweeen thoſe two States was ſome difference about Matters of Commerce, and whilſt the <hi>King of England</hi> was Arming, the <hi>French King</hi> offer'd to <hi>engage</hi> in a <hi>Treaty</hi> with <hi>Holland,</hi> on purpoſe to amuſe and divert them from putting themſelves in a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture of Defence, as they ſoon after perceived; when <hi>France</hi> inſtead of conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Treaty, begun with them, declared himſelf for <hi>England;</hi> and whilſt the latter Attacked them by Sea, he Invaded their Country with a Puiſſant Army; and ſuppoſing the Conqueſt of thoſe Provinces indubitable, they had afore-hand divided them amongſt themſelves, <hi>England</hi> being to have for his ſhare the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritime Places, and <hi>France</hi> all the reſt: <hi>Amſterdam</hi> only proved a Bone of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, and occaſion'd ſome Difference between them, both the one and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deſiring it for his ſhare: tho indeed they had no reaſon to be in a heat about it, ſeeing all this was but reckoning without their Hoſt, God preſerving it from falling into either of their Hands. Thus a Peace being at laſt concluded with <hi>England,</hi> the Spirit of <hi>France</hi> was at work again to with draw the <hi>States</hi> from their Allies, and finding that things were about to change face, and that the <hi>Outch</hi> being row ſed by a Diſcovery of the Artifices and Treachery of <hi>France,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to look about them, and their Troops having a good General at the Head of them, became conſiderable and formidable, he thought fit for a while to diſmiſs the <hi>Lion</hi> and act the <hi>Fox,</hi> reſtoring <hi>Maeſtricht</hi> unto them, in order to obtain the Peace of <hi>Nimeguen.</hi> Since which time, that King has contented himſelf to bark afar off, and was ſo apprehenſive of the States raiſing the laſt 6000 Men, that <hi>Count d' Avaux</hi> ſpar'd nothing to prevent it, and will do ſo ſtill, as often as the States ſhall go about to Arm themſelves, becauſe that would ſtop the <hi>Great Lewis</hi> in the full Career of his Conqueſts, and make his Deſigns to prove abortive. I ſay again that it is the great Concern of <hi>Holland,</hi> not to ſuffer the <hi>Spaniſh Netherlands</hi> to be loſt, except they deſire at the ſame time to become a prey to the Uſurper. For how eaſily will he find an occaſion of quarrel with them; and if all elſe fail, he will make out his Pretenſions and Right to thoſe Provinces, for that they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly belonged to <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Burgundy, Philip the Firſt, Charles the Fift,</hi> and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to <hi>Philip the Second,</hi> who were without Conteſt the lawful Poſſeſſors there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and that afterwards rebelling, they obtained by force an acknowledgment of their being a free State. He will proffer to maintain them in all their Liberties and Priviledges; and the free Exerciſe of their Religion, in caſe they willingly ſubmit to him; which if they ſhould hearken to, he will by little and little clip their Franchiſes, and remove all Proteſtants from places of Truſt, as he has done
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:57967:6"/>at home; and if they yield not willingly, he will attack them with an armed hand, as he did in 1672, being ſure the <hi>Roman Catholick Princes</hi> will not oppoſe him, becauſe he has blinded their Eyes with the falſe pretence of Religion. But if the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> be not aware be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times of the Snares he lays for them under theſe ſpecious Pretexts, they will find themſelves deceiv'd when it is too late to recall their Inadvertency. To return to the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces,</hi> I ſay, they ought, next to God, not to rely upon any thing ſo much as their own Forces, and having nothing ſo much to fear as <hi>France,</hi> they ought to provide and ſtrengthen themſelves againſt his Power chiefly, who has, for this great while, been plotting and contriving their final Overthrow, or, at leaſt, the bringing of them ſo low, as to be forced to depend ſolely upon, and truckle under him. It has ſome time ſince been obſerv'd, that <hi>France</hi> has had a ſtrong de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to make <hi>Holland</hi> liſten to the Propoſal and Treaty, which the <hi>Wolf</hi> in the <hi>Fable</hi> made with the <hi>Sheep, Put away from you</hi> (ſaid the <hi>Wolf</hi> to thoſe harmleſs Creatures) <hi>your Shepherd and Dog, and we will make an Alliance, and live in Love and Amity together.</hi> In like manner, ſays Lewis <hi>the Great, Diſmiſs your General, and Disband your Old Troops; for to what purpoſe theſe unneceſſary Charges in a time of Peace; eſpecially being ſo well aſſur'd of our Friendſhip, by the Truce I am engaged in, and the word of a King, which you may ſafely rely on, that we will live in all Amity and good Correſpondence with you.</hi> But what ſays the <hi>Italian, Truſt not, if thou wouldſt not be cheated.</hi> So that it is ſtill ſafeſt for <hi>Holland</hi> to rely wholly on its own ſtrength, and to have always a good Fleet at Sea, to ſerve for Convoy and Cruiſing, beſides a Reſerve in readineſs to join with them in caſe of need. A good Navy may well be call'd the Right hand of that Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, being of great uſe in diſpelling many Clouds and ill Deſigns which <hi>France</hi> hatcheth againſt his Neighbours. And if ever the <hi>States</hi> ſhould come to a Reſolution continually to keep in Pay a certain Number of Seamen, to be ready to be put aboard their Men of War at any time, this would produce a double good Effect. The firſt is, that the <hi>States</hi> would always have Men ready at hand upon occaſion (without the Expence of Trouble and Time in raiſing them) who, by their continual Employment, would be trained up, and well uſed to the Sea, and Naval Conflicts. The ſecond is, that by this means they would not fail to draw a great number of Seamen from the Neighbouring Coaſts, continual Pay being no ſmall Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to Mariners, to betake themſelves to the Service of thoſe that offer it, but more eſpecially the <hi>States</hi> Subjects in Foreign Service, would not fail to return to their own Country, to enjoy the benefit of being maintain'd all the year round. To effect which, the <hi>States</hi> need only to publiſh a <hi>Placaet,</hi> ſtrictly enjoining all Seamen, their Subjects, in Foreign Service, to return home. True indeed it is, that the Navy of <hi>France</hi> will but be little the better for it; for I dare affirm, they can fit out very few Men of War, without putting ſome <hi>Dutch</hi> Mariners, eſpecially Pilots aboard them, as truſting more to their Knowledge and Experience than their own, who are oft at a loſs in a long Voyage. Which good and wholſom Reſolution, when ever the <hi>States</hi> ſhall be pleaſe to take, you'l preſently ſee the Spirit of <hi>France</hi> ſtrangely exaſperated and diſturb'd, and his Ambaſſador running from one City to another to repreſent his Maſter's juſt Reaſons againſt it. But 'tis hoped, that as the Count <hi>d' Avaux</hi> has much laid open himſelf to an obvious diſcovery, by the ſmall Effects his Promiſes have had hitherto, as not being ſcaſon'd with the Salt of Truth and Honeſty, (the main thing that keeps up the Credit and Reputation of a Miniſter in Foreign Countries) ſo he'l do nothing but catch cold. However, I cannot deny but the <hi>French King</hi> is beholden to that <hi>Creat Miniſter</hi> for his having inſpired a Fondneſs for <hi>France</hi> into the minds of ſeveral of the <hi>States</hi> Subjects, which their Lordſhips have no reaſon to thank him for. Beſides this, <hi>France</hi> receives no ſmall ſervice from the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> and other Foreign <hi>Prieſts,</hi> reſiding in the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces,</hi> who have Penſions allow'd them, to pry into, and engage the Inclinations of many there. Theſe <hi>Spies</hi> are in the <hi>Prince's Court,</hi> where they have Friends that ſerve them on occaſion, and have the Impudence to boaſt, <hi>That they are informed of the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:57967:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>very Secrets of the Cabinet.</hi> How many of this ſort of Cattle are there in the States Troops and Gariſons, who have their Correſpondents at the <hi>Hague,</hi> where the General Office of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence is kept, as being the Centre of that Government. This is a thing that ought to be more narrowly lookt to, theſe Spies being no other but the <hi>Emiſſaries</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> who is always reſtleſs, and ſpares nothing that may further his Deſigns. I remember that not long ſince 4 Ducatoons a week were proffer'd a Servant of a <hi>Deputy of the State,</hi> only to report what he heard from his Maſter, at Table, or in Converſation with others; but the Servant, with ſharp words rejected the Proffer, as became an honeſt Man.</p>
               <p>This Inſtance ſhews, that <hi>France</hi> ſets upon People every way, and that therefore one had need always to ſtand upon his Guard to avoid the Blow. I have alſo obſerv'd, that there are another ſort of <hi>petty Spies</hi> that run up and down the chief Towns, eſpecially the <hi>Hague,</hi> daily ſhifting their Ordinaries, except they find occaſion to ſtay longer, and are in proſpect of ſome advantage to be reap'd there of whom thoſe who are oblig'd to frequent ſuch Houſes ought to beware. Others intrude themſelves into Companies, or reſort to the <hi>Court,</hi> and go to ſee the <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>Princeſs</hi> at Dinner and Supper, to hear and ſee what is ſaid or done there; and as ſoon as they have heard or ſeen any thing of concern, you ſee them run like Foot boys to the <hi>French Ambaſſador's,</hi> who, for a Reward, invites them to ſtay and eat with him, he now enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining ſcarce any but ſuch at his Table. I could name a dozen of them who, to my know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, are employ'd in this way, beſides thoſe that do it more ſecretly, and go to the Offering only at Night, and through the Stable door. Count <hi>de Caravas,</hi> one of theſe Spies of great Note, though (in my judgment) of as little uſe, was not ſo cautious, who coming from <hi>Court,</hi> would go into the Ambaſſador's at the Fore-door, in the middle of the day, to communicate to him his Collections. Two perſons, whom I know to be <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> thô in the Garb of Officers, reſort every day to the <hi>Princes</hi> Riſing, Dinner and Supper, and continually attend the Court, where they have ſo many Friends, or at leaſt ſo much cunning, as to be able to procure their <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Friends</hi> ſome Employment who are all <hi>Emiſſaries of France,</hi> and wholly devoted to the ſervice of that King. Others have put themſelves to ſerve even in the Kitchin where ſuch ſort of Cattle are very dangerous. Therefore I conclude, that both the <hi>States</hi> and <hi>Prince of Orange,</hi> ought in all Reſpects, and at all Times, to be very cautious of the wicked and unchri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Maxims and Deſigns of <hi>France,</hi> the King himſelf being a falſe and perjur'd perſon, who, under pretence of eſtabliſhing the <hi>Roman Catholick Religion</hi> everywhere, (thô by his wicked Life and breach of Faith he denies all Religion) has no other aim, but to extend his Dominion to the uttermoſt Bounds of <hi>Europe,</hi> and to that end deſtroy firſt all the <hi>Proteſtant Princes,</hi> and then the <hi>Roman Catholick</hi> too that ſo he may cauſe himſelf to be proclaimed, not the <hi>Emperor</hi> of the <hi>Romans</hi> only, but of all <hi>Europe;</hi> and certain it is, that nothing can ſerve him as a Bridge to the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Monarchy</hi> but <hi>Holland,</hi> which from his <hi>Verſailles</hi> he looks upon with a moſt envious Eye. So that the States and People of thoſe Provinces have great reaſon to mind the advice of our Saviour to the <hi>Jews, Watch, for you know not what hour the Thief will come.</hi> To which I add, <hi>Be ready therefore to oppoſe him when he ſhall come to break into the Houſe, and uſurp his Neighbours Territories: and be ſure to look upon</hi> France <hi>as a ſworn Enemy to</hi> Republicks, <hi>and the Plague and Scourge of all that will not yield their Liberties up to him.</hi> True it is, he ſears the <hi>States,</hi> more than he loves them, care therefore muſt be taken to be always in ſuch a condition as may ſtill keep him ſo, and to make him know himſelf, when ever he ſhall ſo far forget him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf as to meddle with what he has nothing to do. All the Remonſtrances made by Count <hi>d' Avaux,</hi> as ſoon as he ſees the <hi>States</hi> putting themſelves into a poſture of Defence, muſt not be minded, as being meerly upon deſign; for we may be ſure that Miniſter would not make them, were it not for the promoting of his Maſters Intereſts.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:57967:7"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
